<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the trade to the East Indies together with the state of the present company, and the best method for establishing and managing that trade to the honor and advantage of the nation / written by Mr. George White, of London, merchant ...</title>
            <author>White, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39756</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18482837</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18482837</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107843</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107843)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1644:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the trade to the East Indies together with the state of the present company, and the best method for establishing and managing that trade to the honor and advantage of the nation / written by Mr. George White, of London, merchant ...</title>
                  <author>White, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCI [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East India Company.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  East Indies.</term>
               <term>East Indies --  Commerce --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107843:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107843:1"/>
            <p>An ACCOUNT of the TRADE TO THE EAST-INDIES, Together With <hi>The State of the Preſent Company,</hi> AND THE BEST METHOD FOR <hi>Eſtabliſhing</hi> and <hi>Managing</hi> That TRADE TO THE Honor and Advantage OF THE NATION.</p>
            <p>Written By Mr. <hi>GEORGE WHITE,</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> MERCHANT. At the Deſire of ſeveral MEMBERS of Both Houſes of PARLIAMENT:</p>
            <p>AND Now made Publick, for <hi>General Information</hi> in an Affair of ſo <hi>Great Concern</hi> to the WHOLE KINGDOM.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the YEAR, MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:107843:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107843:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable AND Moſt Honoured Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Eſteem'd my ſelf very much honour'd, when your Deſire of converſing with me about the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade was firſt ſignified to me by a worthy Gentleman. And I muſt always acknowledg your obliging Condeſcentions at my Attendance on you, when you were pleas'd to enjoyn me to give you the Subſtance of my Diſcourſe in Writing, that you might make uſe of it as you found requiſite for the publick Service. I am proud of your good Opinion in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming my mean Performances worthy the leaſt regard, and in Obedience to your Command, I now preſent you with this Paper, which, however wanting in other Reſpects, brings nothing but what, upon the ſtricteſt Aſſay, will be found to come up to the Standard of Sincerity and Truth.</p>
            <p>The ENQUIRIES you were pleaſed to make of me are Theſe;
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Whether the Trade to the</hi> Eaſt-Indies <hi>was really of ſuch great</hi> Advantage <hi>to the</hi> Nation, <hi>as general Diſcourſe repreſented it?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Concerning the</hi> Conſtitution, Management <hi>and</hi> Condition <hi>of the</hi> preſent Company. <hi>And</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>My Opinion of the</hi> moſt proper Manner and Method for ſetling that Trade to the Honour and Intereſt of the Kingdom.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. Firſt, as to the <hi>Trade in general.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Concerning which, I will only preſent the few following Intimations, and refer to your great Judgment to make an Eſtimate of what Import and Benefit it may be to the Nation.</p>
               <p>The Traffick to thoſe Parts of the World, which are compriz'd in the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company's Charter, will employ a Capital of <hi>Twelve hundred Thouſand Pounds.</hi> And after I have ſaid that, 'tis needleſs to obſerve to you, how conſiderably it will aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the <hi>Publick Revenue</hi> of the Cuſtoms.</p>
               <p>It will annually export to amount of about <hi>l.</hi> 150000: in Woollen Cloths, Lead, and other Commodities of our <hi>native Growth</hi> and <hi>Manufacture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It will employ about <hi>Twenty five Capital Ships,</hi> and therein about <hi>Three thouſand Seamen:</hi> and theſe Ships will be of ſuch Force and Burthen that may render them ſerviceable as well in Occaſion of <hi>War,</hi> as Affairs of <hi>Merchandize.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis by this Trade alone we can be ſupply'd with vaſt Quantities of <hi>Saltpeter</hi> at cheap Rates, which in the Age we live, is of it ſelf a ſufficient Recommendation.</p>
               <p>This Trade do's not only ſupply us with Varieties of Goods for our neceſſary Uſe and Ornament; But the greater Part of the Commodities brought from <hi>India</hi> are exported to ſundry Parts in <hi>Europe, Africa</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> which does further advance our <hi>Navigation</hi> and <hi>Commerce.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:107843:3"/>
               <p>It will give Employment to about <hi>Two hundred Merchants, Factors</hi> and <hi>Writers,</hi> who will have good Opportunities of advancing their Fortunes; and 'tis not to be doubted, that many of them may return with plentiful Eſtates, which will contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Wealth and Strength of the Nation, as well as their own particular Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Benefit.</p>
               <p>This Trade, as well in regard to the publick Honor, as the particular Intereſt of the Adventurers, requires to be negotiated with a <hi>National Ioynt-Stock,</hi> which will render it more <hi>diffuſive:</hi> For by that means it will not be engroſs'd into the hands of thoſe who are profeſs'd <hi>Merchants,</hi> but our <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> may partake of the Profit, without any Diminution of their <hi>Dignity,</hi> or Diſturbance to their <hi>Eaſe:</hi> For their Talents will be improvd' with no more trouble than to receive the good Fruits of their Adventures, which with large Allowance for adverſe Accidents may modeſtly be computed at 20 <hi>l. per Cent. per annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Objections</hi> have been rais'd againſt this Trade: there are only <hi>Three</hi> that I know of worth the leaſt notice, and they ſo, only becauſe they have made a popular Noiſe, while the true Merits of the Cauſe have not been duly examin'd and conſider'd by thoſe whom they have rendred diſaffected to this noble and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial Commerce.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) The firſt and great Complaint is: That is carries out ſuch vaſt Quantities of our <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver.</hi> And here I muſt confeſs, that to manage this Trade in its due Currency; 'twill require that the Stock employ'd in it be at leaſt Three Fourths in Bullion, and ſo it may be computed: That a <hi>general Ioynt-Stock</hi> together with what may be adventured for <hi>Diamonds</hi> and other Things, that will be found moſt proper to be permitted for particular Accounts, may together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to about Six hundred thouſand Pounds <hi>per annum.</hi> But after all, 'Tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs true, that this do's not only not in the leaſt <hi>diminiſh</hi> our Mony; But contrarily, That by the Circulation of Trade it much <hi>augments</hi> the Treaſure of the Nation in the Species of Gold and Silver. This may perhaps at firſt ſight look like a ſtrange <hi>Paradox,</hi> but I will exhibit a plain Proof by matter of Fact, which will render it indubitable. From the Year 1675 to 83 incluſive there was ſhip'd out by the Company and Private Traders the amount of about <hi>Four Millions and a half</hi> in Bullion of Gold and Silver; and I find upon Enquiry, there was likewiſe in that circuit of time coin'd in the Tower above <hi>Four Millions</hi> more. So that in the firſt place it appears: The great Exportations to <hi>India</hi> did not then occaſion any Want in the Mint; And, that there were alſo in thoſe Years prodigious Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of <hi>Plate</hi> converted into <hi>Houſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils,</hi> and conſum'd in the Ornaments and Gallantries of the Great and Rich, is too apparent to need a Proof. And laſtly, That we then had ſuperabundant <hi>Plenty of Caſh current</hi> in the Nation, is evident in that, tho the Law allows the Uſurer to take Six <hi>per Cent.</hi> we all know Mony went about begging Securities at Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> and vaſt Summs were lent out at Four <hi>per Cent.</hi> And that I may here fully evince this great Truth, I muſt further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That for theſe laſt four or five Years, wherein our Company have left off their good old Trade of <hi>Merchandize,</hi> and apply'd themſelves to the <hi>Art of War,</hi> they have ſent out little or nothing in Gold or Silver; and yet I ſee not the leaſt Appearance that Bullion or Coin has ſince increas'd upon us, but rather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. So that upon the whole matter this Objection has only given an Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to make it manifeſt. <hi>That the Trade to India is a moſt exuberant Source to repleniſh our Treaſuries as well as our Ware-Houſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Another Objection is, That this Trade do's not take off greater Quantities of our <hi>Woollen Manufactures.</hi> But they who quarrel it on that account ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this irrefragable Maxim, That <hi>Trade is no more to be forc'd than Faith:</hi> and, as we <hi>believe</hi> according to the Dictates of our <hi>Conſciences;</hi> ſo we <hi>buy</hi> and <hi>ſell</hi> both as to Quantities and Sortments, as our <hi>Intereſt</hi> directs. Wherefore tho we may wiſh that Market would vend more of our <hi>home-made Goods,</hi> yet methinks we have no more Reaſon to fall quite out with it on that Score, than becauſe our Ships do not return intirely laden with <hi>Pearls</hi> and <hi>Diamonds.</hi> I have before intimated what
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107843:3"/>I am ſure will in fact prove true in this matter, and I may take this Occaſion to add, That I have good ground to hope ſomething more conſiderable may hereafter be done in it, by induſtrious and proper Applications.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) The third Complaint is: That theſe <hi>tedious</hi> and <hi>unhealthy Voyages</hi> deſtroy great numbers of our <hi>Seamen.</hi> And indeed I muſt own, That by ſome <hi>late unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Proceedings</hi> there has been too much Cauſe for this Clamor, which I wiſh they whom it concerns, would ſeriouſly conſider, and bethink themſelves what Anſwer they can make for that Blood will certainly be requir'd at their hands in another World, however they may ſcape with Impunity in this. For many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of our Seamen have been ſacrific'd to the <hi>irrational Obſtinacy</hi> and <hi>wicked Deſigns</hi> of thoſe who have aſſum'd an <hi>arbitrary Predominancy</hi> over the Companies Affairs; By ſending out Ships at moſt improper Seaſons, and detaining them in the <hi>Indies</hi> on occaſion of the <hi>unhappy</hi> and <hi>unjuſtifiable War</hi> with the Great <hi>Mogul</hi> and his Subjects. This is the <hi>real Truth</hi> of the Thing; and the diſmal Mortality has of late happen'd amongſt our Men imploy'd to <hi>India,</hi> is ſo far from being juſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable to the <hi>Tediouſneſs</hi> of the Voyage or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhealthineſs</hi> of the Places we trade to, That I may ſafely affirm, (becauſe I am ſure I have the concurring Evidence of our experienc'd Commanders, who are the beſt Judges of it) That there is no Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion uſed by our Nation, loſes fewer Men, than our Indian Voyages, when Ships are <hi>duly diſpatch'd,</hi> and detain'd in the Country no longer, than the <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Management</hi> of our Mercantile Affairs do's require.</p>
               <p>This is what I have to repreſent in relation to the firſt Demand, and humbly referring it to your judicious Cenſure, I proceed to the Second:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II. Concerning the <hi>Conſtitution, Management</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>Preſent Company.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The <hi>preſent Eaſt-India-Stock</hi> was firſt incorporated in the Year 1657. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though 'tis true, that the Trade has never been improv'd to that <hi>National Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> and with ſuch regard to <hi>Poſterity,</hi> as may juſtly entitle the Managers to the Character of <hi>Publick-ſpirited Patriots;</hi> yet it muſt be confeſs'd, That thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen who had the Conduct of theſe Affairs for about Twenty Years, did ſo well diſcharge themſelves, <hi>To keep the Trade alive, tho they did not induſtriouſly aſſiſt it's Growth;</hi> And to their Honor be it ſaid, They were always very careful to preſerve the main Baſis of our Dependencies firm and entire: And that was our <hi>Credit</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> with the Natives, which by their juſt and punctual deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings had impreſs'd in that People ſuch a high Opinion of our Candor and Probity, that we were preferr'd in their Eſteem, before any other <hi>Europeans;</hi> living amongſt them with great Security to our Perſons and Eſtates, and enjoying very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Immunities in our Commerce.</p>
               <p>The firſt Subſcriptions to the general Stock amounted to about <hi>l.</hi> 739782: But it pleas'd thoſe, who then over-rul'd the Affair, to take in but a Moyety of it, <hi>which ſo cramp'd the grand Enterprize in its Infancy, that it could never ſince be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to its full Dimenſions.</hi> This was the fatal Error in the beginning, which has done ſuch irreparable Prejudice to us, and ineſtimable Benefit to our Neighbours. For had thoſe Conductors been endow'd with ſo much Magnanimity to call in the other part, and beſtow'd all in impregnable Fortifications on their <hi>Spice Iſland</hi> of <hi>Polloroon.</hi> They had merited to have their happy Memories celebrated amongſt us by glorious and laſting Monuments. For by that means we had not only been Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Fruitful Plantations of thoſe Rich Spices, <hi>Mace</hi> and <hi>Nutmegs,</hi> to ſerve our own Expence, and help ſupply the World; But this had been a commodious Seat for an Emporium of Trade to the adjacent Countries, which would have bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then'd us with Wealth. And I will not doubt, but I may (without overvaluing the Abilities of my Countrymen) declare my Opinion, That if this grand Affair had been under the Conduct of Perſons of Skill and Courage, which might have been ſound amongſt us, we had long ere this gain'd the Aſcendent over another <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pean</hi> Nation, who have ſet up their Standard near this place: Becauſe the Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107843:4"/>and Courteſie which is native to a true Engliſh Spirit, could not have fail'd to obtain far more advantageous Conqueſts, than the others have effected by <hi>rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er means.</hi> For we ſhall always find, That as long as Self-Preſervation and deſire of Liberty are the genuine inſtinct of Human Nature, <hi>The Cords of Love will bind faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than Fetters of Iron.</hi> But alas! this fruitful Garden lay neglected for fear of the Charge of Cultivating and Fencing it: For all the Company did, was to ſend out what may more properly be called the Model of a Wooden Fort, than the thing itſelf, and that was <hi>ſet up for a Show.</hi> So that in the Year 64, when the late K. <hi>Charles</hi> made War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> They only ſent a ſmall Ship from <hi>Batavia,</hi> which had nothing elſe to do, but quietly to take Poſſeſſion and remove about Twelve of our People they found there, to new Lodgings at their foreſaid City.</p>
               <p>I could alſo here remember how much our <hi>Firſt Movers</hi> were wanting to the Nation and themſelves, in neglecting to recover their Right to a Moyety of the Cuſtoms at the Port of <hi>Gombroon</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> which was granted to their Predeceſſors for aſſiſting the <hi>Sophie</hi> to take <hi>Ormuze</hi> from the <hi>Portugueſe.</hi> And 'twas indeed a very valuable Acquiſition: For in the Years 1671 and 72 when I was there, the Cuſtoms amounted to about 80000 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi> And tho our Agent did then ſit in the Cuſtom Houſe when he pleas'd, and ſome of the Companies Servants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly attended there, to take exact account of the Income, yet we were ſo <hi>good Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd</hi> to accept of about <hi>l.</hi> 3000: for our half of that great Sum; whereas had our Company at their beginning duly conſider'd their Intereſt, and dar'd to <hi>throw ſo much Bread upon the Waters</hi> as would have defray'd the Expence of an Embaſſage to that Court, by ſome Perſon well qualified for the Occaſion, I cannot doubt, but we might have ſucceſsfully aſſerted our juſt Claim. But after this long In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval without any effectual Motion on our Part, I fear Preſcription may be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a Law againſt us: And yet I would not quite deſpair, but when it ſhall pleaſe Their Majeſties and the Parliament to ſettle this <hi>invaluable Trade</hi> on a good Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, and in the Hands of able and Honeſt Managers, It would be worth the attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to retrieve this loſt Stake, If we could find out ſome excellent Perſon for the purpoſe, who can but Copy after Sir <hi>Thomas Row</hi> formerly at the Court of the Great Mogul, or Sir <hi>William Huſſey</hi> at preſent with the Grand Signior.</p>
               <p>And now, from theſe Intimations of what the firſt Managers of our Company leſt <hi>undone,</hi> I come to take notice of ſomething they <hi>did,</hi> which has prov'd much more injurious and deſtructive; For by the former we only loſt a Part, but the fatal Conſequence of this has hazarded the entire ruin of all our Trade and Intereſt in thoſe Parts, I mean that pernicious Uſage of <hi>Multiplying their Votes accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Stocks,</hi> rating every Vote at <hi>l.</hi> 500:</p>
               <p>This evil practice had it's being with the preſent Company, and was never us'd by the former Joint-Stocks to <hi>India,</hi> nor in any other publick Society that ever I heard of, till This firſt gave it Birth: And 'tis worthy a Remark, the Ingenious Hypotheſis they have fram'd for the Ground of this Projection, whereby they hope to lick over the <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Monſter</hi> into the Shapes of a reaſonable Creature, by ſuch ſlight inſinuations as theſe: <hi>That the Stock ought to govern the Stock; and thoſe who have moſt Mony in it, ſhould have moſt Power in the Diſpoſe and Direction of it.</hi> But a little ſerious Thought will fully diſcover the Iniquity of this falſe bottom'd Argument. I am ſure, 'Tis utterly deſtructive of our <hi>Darling Property,</hi> and directly contrary to thoſe Meaſures which the Juſtice and Wiſdom of the Nation has taken in choice of our Repreſentatives, who are the Preſervers of it. But ſurely there can need no more Verbal Confutation, ſince we know it by its Fruits, and ſuch woful Experience has prov'd, <hi>That he who has the biggeſt Purſe, is not always the moſt Honeſt, nor able to manage ſo weighty an Affair.</hi> For,</p>
               <p>'Tis by this means, that one of our Fellow-Subjects did about 14 years ago mount himſelf into the Supremacy, and has ever ſince uſurp'd an abſolute Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over all the other Adventurers.</p>
               <p>'Tis by this means ſuch great Havock has been made of the <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> as has been repreſented by <hi>numerous Petitions</hi> to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in every Seſſion ſince the late happy Revolution.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:107843:4"/>
               <p>'Tis by this means ſuch <hi>notorious Frauds</hi> have been acted in underſelling the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany's Goods by <hi>Private Contracts and unheard of Deductions afterwards;</hi> whereby it can be prov'd, that the Joynt-Stock has been wrong'd above <hi>One Hundred thouſand Pounds,</hi> in two or three years laſt paſt. Surely thoſe Gentlemen that make ſuch haſt to be rich by theſe oblique ways, never ſeriouſly ask'd themſelves that great Queſtion: <hi>Quid prodeſt homini, ſi mundum univerſum lucretur? &amp;c.</hi> For beſides the common Obligation to <hi>Honeſty,</hi> there is no Member of the Committee, but has twico plighted his Faith by two ſolemn <hi>Oaths</hi> to be true to the Company.</p>
               <p>'Tis by this means that ſo many injur'd Perſons groan under <hi>heavy Oppreſſions,</hi> and can obtain no <hi>Relief;</hi> for if the Concern be not very conſiderable, 'tis adding Grief to Affliction to content it at Law, there are ſuch Tricks and Contrivances practis'd to render the Suit tedious and expenſive, which has put many Perſons upon chooſing the leſs Evil, in referring Matters to ſome of their own <hi>Committee;</hi> and yet ſometimes even that Condeſcenſion has not prevail'd, for there has appear'd ſo great an Averſion from doing any thing like Juſtice and Reaſon, that the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Oſſer of a Reference to a principal Perſon in the Committee has been rejected, as was lately taken notice of, in the high Court of Chancery, on occaſion of a Motion made by a Complainant againſt them, before the Lords Commiſſioners; when the Right Honorable Sir <hi>John Trevor</hi> was pleas'd to declare his Senſe of their <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>arbitrary Oppreſſions,</hi> reprehending them for their illegal Seizures of the Ships and Goods of their fellow Subjects, who were honeſtly employing themſelves and their Eſtates in their Trade of Merchandize; and reproving them for the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods he obſerv'd they took to delay and evade making Reſtitution to thoſe they had wrong'd; and he then told them he was inform'd of a certain Perſon, who had a matter depending with them. And frankly offer'd to refer it entirely to Sir <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Herne</hi> the preſent Governour, which was refus'd; and indeed it ought to be recorded to the Honour of that Worthy Gentleman, and the Infamy of thoſe who oppos'd his being intruſted with the Affair; for the Reaſon of it is very obvious, Becauſe there could not be the leaſt Pretence to doubt of his doing the utmoſt for them, that could poſſibly conſiſt with <hi>right Reaſon,</hi> His own Intereſt and his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them, doubly obliging him to it: But <hi>Some Body</hi> was jealous that his Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue would influence his Inclinations, and reſtrain him from taking greater Lengths in their Favour than Equity and good Conſcience could extend to. And for that Cauſe he was no fit Perſon for the Purpoſe.</p>
               <p>'Tis by this means, that the Trade has not only of late been let out to <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Men</hi> amongſt our ſelves, but <hi>Foreigners</hi> have been invited into <hi>England,</hi> to lade their private Stocks on the Companies Shipping; which can bear no other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, but that either they have made ſuch <hi>over-large Dividends,</hi> as has not left a <hi>ſufficient Fund</hi> of their own to carry on the Trade; or thoſe amongſt them, who do what they pleaſe with all their Affairs, make ſome <hi>particular Advantage</hi> to themſelves by this publick <hi>Scandal</hi> to the <hi>Nation,</hi> and <hi>Detriment</hi> to the <hi>Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis by this means, our noble <hi>Trade</hi> has degenerated into <hi>Trick,</hi> and inſtead of employing a Stock in honeſt and generous Adventures abroad, according to the laudable Practice of Merchants; There is lately ſet up a new Society of <hi>Artificers,</hi> who blow the Price of Stock up and down, as beſt ſuits their Deſign of enriching themſelves by the ruin of others; and this <hi>Legerdemain</hi> is manng'd by a ſtrange ſort of <hi>Inſects</hi> call'd <hi>Stock-Iobbers,</hi> who devour men on our <hi>Exchange,</hi> as the <hi>Locuſts</hi> of old did the Herbage of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But all theſe and many more the like evil Effects of <hi>Plurality of Votes</hi> will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear very inconſiderable, when we exhibit that one monſtrous Production of <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king War with the Great Mogul and the King of Syam.</hi> As to the latter of theſe, I have formerly preſented the Honorable Houſe of Commons with the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Grounds of it, and prov'd, that there is not the leaſt ſhadow of Reaſon to help extenuate, much leſs juſtifie that <hi>unaccountable Quarrel;</hi> nor can I poſſibly imagine what ſhould provoke our Indignation againſt that obliging Prince, unleſs it were becauſe thoſe rich Preſents, which the chief Miniſter in that Court did by my means make to the two late Kings, were not rather directed to <hi>Wanſtead</hi> than <hi>Whitehall.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107843:5"/>
               <p>Now concerning the Violences have been done to the People of <hi>Suratt</hi> and <hi>Bengale<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> in plundering them by Sea and Land, which has been call'd by the name of a <hi>War with the Great Mogul,</hi> The naked Truth of the thing is this:</p>
               <p>There had been very ill Meaſures taken for ſeveral years together in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the <hi>Joynt Stock,</hi> which had brought it into a <hi>deep Conſumption.</hi> I will inſtance in three or four of the principal.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the taking up ſuch <hi>immenſe Sums at Intereſt.</hi> For ſometimes they have ow'd above a Million here in <hi>England,</hi> and 'twas ſeldom they were not alſo conſiderably indebted in <hi>India.</hi> This was a conſtant conſuming Charge and a direct Damage to the Company, if their Stock were <hi>really</hi> worth but the <hi>Original Subſcription,</hi> when 'twas <hi>verbally</hi> valu'd at above <hi>Two Millions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another thing was, The great <hi>Expence</hi> in making Intereſt at Court to procure a Power to deſtroy both Fellow-Subjects and Foreigners: For beſides the ſeveral Ten Thouſand Guineas to the two late Kings, there was a far greater amount to the <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Favo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ites;</hi> inſomuch, that I am certainly inform'd the Charge now ſtands in their Books at a vaſt Sum under the Title of <hi>Secret Services.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this may be added the great Prejudice done the Stock by ſeveral capricious and coſtly <hi>Projects,</hi> and ſuch inexcuſable <hi>Miſmanagement,</hi> In employing Perſons wholly unfit for the Buſineſs, Unneceſſary charge of Dead Freight and Demorage; And ſuch ſtrange improper Quantities and ſorts of Goods ſent out and ordered home; That tho I cannot poſitively affirm the Promoters of theſe ill things were in Combination with the Companies profeſt Enemies, yet this I may ſafely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. That if they had receiv'd very conſiderable <hi>Marks of Esteem</hi> (as the <hi>French</hi> Phraſe it) from thoſe who long'd for their Deſtruction, they could not have more effectually contributed to it.</p>
               <p>But above all things of this kind, that which devour'd the Stock by wholeſale, was the moſt unreaſonable and unjuſt <hi>Dividends,</hi> which were made without the leaſt regard to any real Advance produc'd by the Trade, but as <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice</hi> were pleaſed to command; for in the compaſs of Five Years, which was from <hi>February</hi> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>January</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi> ½ they drew out <hi>l</hi> 741647 and in Two Months after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they doubled their Stock. which together made <hi>l.</hi> 1109673: and all this from a Capital of <hi>l.</hi> 369891: which was the principal Mony pay'd in by the Adventurers: And if we here further conſider, that in this Interim they were moreover at the Charge of above <hi>l.</hi> 300000: for Money borrowed at Intereſt and <hi>Complements to Friends at Court,</hi> It does all together look ſo very ſtrange, that I think it would well deſerve to be eſteem'd the <hi>Eighth Wonder of the World,</hi> had it not ſoon after appear'd, that they made <hi>more haſt</hi> than <hi>good Speed</hi> in this prodigious Carreer, which ſubjected it to the common Fate of all thoſe Motions, that are more violent than the Nature of the Thing will bear. For by theſe ways and means the Stock was brought into that languiſhing Condition, and in ſuch a ſad manner exhauſted, that 'twas apparent, Thoſe who manag'd the Affair had their Thoughts ſo wholly employ'd about the buſineſs of <hi>dividing,</hi> that they quite forgot to leave any Mony behind to ſatisfie their <hi>Debts;</hi> for inſtead of continuing thoſe <hi>punctual Payments</hi> which till then had preſerv'd their Credit in its <hi>Virgin Purity,</hi> they did ſoon after <hi>proſtitute their Reputation</hi> by affixing a Paper on the Treaſury Door, declaring that they cou'd not pay any more Mony till after ſome Months time, which, for the <hi>Preſumption</hi> and the <hi>Scandal</hi> of it, is perhaps without a Precedent.</p>
               <p>And here we have found the right Key to the Myſtery of the War with the <hi>Mogul:</hi> For things being brought to this ſad paſs, 'twas now high time to caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout how to repair the Ruins: And the happy <hi>Expedient</hi> reſolv'd on, was to ſeize on the rich Fleets belonging to <hi>Suratt,</hi> and more eſpecially thoſe that traded to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> But there was alſo an ingenious Contrivance antecedent to this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that was, To gain an Advantage by the Friendſhip we had with theſe People, before we treated them as Enemies. In making uſe of the Companies Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, to borrow about <hi>l.</hi> 300000: and then retire to <hi>Bombay</hi> to make Spoil of their Ships and Goods. And to ſtimulate their chief Factor Mr. <hi>Child</hi> to proſecute this great Work with the higheſt degree of Zeal and Diligence, there was procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for him a Patent for a Baronet, with a Commiſſion, ſtyling him <hi>General
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107843:5"/>of all his Majeſty's Forces by Sea and Land in the Northern Parts of India, Perſia and Arabia &amp;c.</hi> The Commanders of the Ships had likewiſe the Kings Commiſſion, with leave to wear the Royal Enſigns; All which together ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd ſo abſurd and ridiculous, that as an ingenuous Gentleman writes from thence <hi>Our Neighbours the French and Dutch could not put themſelves into a Poſture of laughing enough at it:</hi> but while they laugh'd, our Company won (at leaſt it was then thought ſo:) For beſides a great number of ſmaller Veſſels, they took about 13 conſiderable Ships to amount of above a Million Sterling, as has been Sworn in their Majeſties Court of Exchecquer, and the value of about <hi>l.</hi> 300000: of it has been brought home, as can be prov'd by the Confeſſion of one of the prime Agents in the preſent Committee.</p>
               <p>Now all theſe Proceedings were not only moſt unjuſtifiable, for that they had not in reality receiv'd any Injuries that requir'd ſuch Reparations, Nor did they apply to the <hi>Mogul</hi> for Redreſs of their pretended Grievances, before they acted thoſe <hi>Hoſtilities</hi> on his Subjects: But the Violence is ſtill further aggravated in regard that ſeveral of the Ships they took had the Security of their own <hi>Paſſes,</hi> and they have made ſeizure of ſome Goods which were laden on board their own Ships on Freight. And altho the prevailing Intereſt of ſome Members of the Committee did in time of the late King procure a Commiſſion to ſet up a Court of Admiralty on their Iſland of <hi>Bombay,</hi> which they made uſe of to confiſcate the Eſtates of their Fellow Subjects, yet to the Ships and Goods belonging to <hi>Suratt,</hi> they did not allow ſo much as the formality of a Tryal and Condemnation, which makes theſe <hi>Captures</hi> look more like <hi>plain Piracy</hi> than <hi>Lawful Prize.</hi> Indeed the whole thing together is ſuch a complicated Evil, That I want a Name for it, <hi>Crimen laeſae Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis &amp; proditae Patriae</hi> will ſcarce reach it: And that our Legiſlators have not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a particular Statute againſt it, and appointed a Puniſhment ſuitable to ſo heinous an Offence; there can be no other Reaſon aſſign'd, but what the Hiſtorian tells us was the Cauſe; That till after the ſecond <hi>Punick</hi> War, there was in the <hi>Roman</hi> Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions no particular Law againſt <hi>Paricide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here after this Account of the <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Progreſs</hi> of our <hi>Martial Exploits,</hi> It may not be amiſs to ſubjoyn an Eſtimate of the <hi>Advantages</hi> have accrued to us thereby, which may be ſumm'd up in the following Particulars.</p>
               <p>It has coſt the Company above <hi>l.</hi> 400000: in ſundry Expences and Charges; as. Advance on the rate of their Tunnage for ſupernumerary Seamen, Tranſporting Soldiers from <hi>England,</hi> with their Pay, and the like of great Numbers raiſed in <hi>India,</hi> Vaſt Quantities of Ammunition and extraordinary Charges of Gariſon in Fort S. <hi>George</hi> and <hi>Bombay,</hi> together with thoſe heavy Articles of <hi>dead Freight</hi> and <hi>Demorage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It has interrupted the courſe of our Traffick for four or five years, whereby the Company (ſuppoſing they had a ſufficient Stock to manage the Trade:) cannot be computed to have loſt leſs than <hi>l.</hi> 800000: and the Crown about <hi>l.</hi> 200000: in Cuſtoms.</p>
               <p>It has occaſion'd the loſs of ſome Thouſands of our good Soldiers and able Seamen.</p>
               <p>It has been the means of deſtroying five conſiderable Ships that we know of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what may be doubted of thoſe which have been ſo long abroad in that unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Service.</p>
               <p>But above all we have thereby loſt that invaluable Jewel, our <hi>Reputation</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect;</hi> and of the moſt belov'd and favour'd are juſtly become moſt abhorr'd and infamous in the Eſteem of that People. There needs no further Proof of this than the very <hi>Phirmaunds</hi> or <hi>Patents</hi> lately granted by the <hi>Mogul,</hi> at our Readmiſſion to Trade in his Countries, which were tranſlated out of <hi>Perſian,</hi> and ſent to the Company by their Factors at <hi>Suratt,</hi> in theſe following Words:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="firman">
                              <pb n="8" facs="tcp:107843:6"/>
                              <head>The PHIRMAUND for <hi>Bengale.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>KNOW this, that the good Fortune of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> hath directed them the right way to end their Faults, they are ſorry and aſham'd for what they have done, therefore have ſent their Vakeels <hi>[Factors]</hi> to our noble Court, with a Petition for a gracious <hi>Phirmaund</hi> to pardon their Faults; which the King out of his great Favour and Mercy always ready to pardon, doth freely forgive them; Therefore his clear and unſpotted Order is ſuch, which you are to obſerve, as you do his that you pray to, That ſo ſoon as this gracious Phirmaund reaches your hands, you ſuffer no body in your Juriſdiction to moleſt, hurt, or hinder the <hi>Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in their Buſineſs, but ſuffer them to carry it on in the ſame manner as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly. This underſtand, and act accordingly.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="firman">
                              <head>The PHIRMAUND for <hi>Suratt.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>ALL the <hi>Engliſh</hi> having made an humble ſubmiſſive Petition, That the ill Crimes they have done may be pardon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>d, and requeſted a noble Phir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund to make their being forgiven manifeſt, and ſent their <hi>Vakeels</hi> to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Palace the moſt illuſtrious in the World, to get the Royal Favour. And <hi>Ettimand Chawn</hi> The Governour of <hi>Suratt</hi>'s Petition to the famous Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>t, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to the Skies, being arriv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>d; That they wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>d preſent the great King with a Fine of <hi>150000</hi> Rupees to his noble Treaſury, reſembling the Sun, and wou'd reſtore the Merchants Goods they took away to the Owners of them, and would walk by the ancient Cuſtoms of the Port, and behave themſelves for the future no more in ſuch a <hi>ſhameful manner:</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Wherefore His Majeſty according to his daily Favour to all People of the World, hath pardon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>d their Faults, mercifully forgiven them, and out of his Princely Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion agrees, That the Preſent be put into the Treaſure of the Port, the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Goods be return'd, the Town flouriſh, and they follow their Trade as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times; and Mr. <hi>Child,</hi> who did the Diſgrace, be turn'd out and expell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>d.</p>
                              <p>This Order is irreverſible.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are their new <hi>Patents,</hi> but may much more properly be ſtyl'd <hi>Gracious Pardons:</hi> And although I am well aſſur'd the <hi>Mahometans</hi> will religiouſly obſerve them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if the Chriſtians that are concern'd do punctually perform the Conditions on their Part; yet certainly there is no Mankind but muſt needs be affected with moſt paſſionate Reſentments, to ſee the Honour of his Mother Country expos'd to this Contempt and Ignominy, and our common Name ſtigmatiz'd with ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious Epithetes; But what ſtill makes the conſideration much more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is, That the <hi>black Characters</hi> are in a manner indelible, for theſe Inſtruments are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited amongſt the Records in the Court of that great Prince, where they are like to remain as long as <hi>God</hi> continues a Being to the World, and ſo the Reproach will be entail'd on our Poſterity, and Generations to come may feel the dire Effects of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107843:6"/>ſubjecting the <hi>Dictates of Reaſon</hi> to the <hi>Power of the Purſe</hi> by the fatal device of <hi>Complicated Votes.</hi> For 'tis by that means alone that our Affairs have been brought into theſe moſt unhappy Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>From which melancholy Relation I proceed to the laſt thing demanded of me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III. Concerning the <hi>moſt proper Manner and Method of eſtabliſhing this opulent Trade, to the Honor and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Nation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>That the Commerce to the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> as well in regard to the publick Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as the Security and Advantage of the Adventurers, requires to be negotiated by a <hi>National Ioynt Stock,</hi> is a great Truth ſo generally receiv'd amongſt our ſelves, and confirm'd by the univerſal Conſent and Practice of other Nations, that 'twou'd be a Tautology to offer any Arguments for Proof of it, and therefore I will here only repeat what I before occaſionally intimated; <hi>That ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution will moſt conduce to the common Good, in communicating the benefits to all Degrees and Profeſſions amongſt us:</hi> So that the Thing now to be conſider'd is, How Juſtice and Prudence will direct us (under the preſent Poſture of Affairs) to lay a good Foundation for this Great Work.</p>
               <p>There has too much been already ſaid (if the <hi>Laws</hi> of Truth cou'd have been <hi>diſpens'd</hi> with) to make it evident, That the <hi>Nation</hi> has ſuſtain'd <hi>irreparable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice</hi> by the Errors of thoſe that have preſided in the Management of the preſent Companies Concerns, who, beſides many other high Miſdemeanors, have divided and conſum'd the Stock in ſuch a manner, that they have not left a <hi>ſufficient Fund</hi> to negotiate the Trade, which will be totally loſt to us, if ſome ſpeedy and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Remedy be not apply'd to ſupport and reeſtabliſh it. But it do's not therefore follow, That the Preſent Stock muſt unavoidably be concluded and broke up, and <hi>another Subſcription</hi> promoted intirely <hi>new</hi> and <hi>ſeparate</hi> from it. Becauſe though the Authors of all this <hi>Miſchief</hi> deſerve to be ſeverely cenſur'd; yet it ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, That there are ſome very honorable Perſonages, and many very worthy Gentlemen intereſted in this Company who ſhou'd not have any thing offer'd to them that do's ſo much as look like the leaſt hard Uſage. And therefore that <hi>equal Right</hi> may be done to all, It ſeems more agreeable, That the <hi>Remains</hi> of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Company, as well <hi>Dead</hi> as <hi>Quick</hi> Stock, be equitably valu'd, with a due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of all their juſt and reaſonable Pretences; And that a <hi>General Subſcription</hi> be made throughout the whole Kingdom, to be conjoyn'd thereto, and this to be incorporated and confirm'd by Act of Parliament as a <hi>National Eaſt-India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> with ſuch Priviledges and under ſuch Regulations as to the great Wiſdom of our Honorable Repreſentatives ſhall ſeem meet.</p>
               <p>And here, tho perhaps it may look like too fond a Conceit of my own Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet I cannot forbear to ſay, That there is no Perſon concern'd in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Stock, who has an <hi>honeſt Intention</hi> directed by a <hi>true Cognizance</hi> of the State of their Affairs, but muſt readily accord to this Propoſal, and not only acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, That 'tis indiſpenſibly requiſite it be done with all poſſible Expedition, But That 'tis likewiſe the utmoſt, Juſtice can allow to be done in their Favor; while at the ſame time I am not ignorant, that there are ſome <hi>Conſpirators</hi> as hard at Work, as ever <hi>Guy Faux</hi> was in the Cellars under the Senate-Houſe, in contriving to get this Company confirm'd at the next Seſſion of Parliament, without any <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection</hi> into their Bottom, or <hi>Reformation</hi> of their notorious Abuſes; and they depend upon ſupplying their want of Stock, by Mony to be taken up at <hi>Intereſt,</hi> which they promiſe themſelves will flow in to them, on the Credit of ſuch an Eſtabliſhment.</p>
               <p>Theſe are a ſort of Men, who Act as if 'twere a principal Article of their Creed, that their main Buſineſs in this World is to aggrandize their Families, though they raiſe their Fortunes by the Ruin of their Country; and they go on with a ſtrange aſſurance of Succeſs to their evil Deſign; for they have cut out a <hi>Bill</hi> in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and preſume they ſhall make an Intereſt for its paſſing without oppoſition;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107843:7"/>whereby one or two aſpiring Men hope to be inveſted with a more <hi>Deſpotick Power</hi> over our Lives and Eſtates, than their Majeſties <hi>aſſume</hi> or <hi>exerciſe</hi> on the Throne; And thus after all the Boaſts we have made to the World of the great <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties</hi> we enjoy, they would make us the moſt abject Slaves in Nature; <hi>For thoſe Impoſings may in ſome reſpect be tolerable from the hand of a Sovereign, which wou'd be worſe than Death from a Fellow-Subject,</hi> eſpecially from ſuch who have not the leaſt Pretence to any Superiority, more, than they fancy they have acquir'd by amaſſing a great deal of Wealth in a little time; whereas this their imaginary <hi>Gain</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> is their real <hi>Loſs</hi> and <hi>Shame,</hi> and ſo eſteem'd by all good Men who have a true ſence of Things, and rightly conſider how their Accounts muſt be audited in another World. Wherefore I cou'd heartily wiſh theſe Gentlemen wou'd recollect, and ingage their Minds and Monies on ſome more laudable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize. Not that I fear that all their <hi>Artifice</hi> and <hi>Influence</hi> can accompliſh their Ends: my ardent Deſire of ſeeing this mighty Trade revive and flouriſh, inſpires me with better hopes, and aſſures me, They ſhall not obtain. For indeed there only wants a publick Repreſentation of things in their proper Colours, to take off that <hi>deceptio Viſus</hi> wherewith they have diſguis'd the Face of Truth; and all their Endeavors will ſoon appear as vain and fruitleſs in their own Eyes, as they are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble and ungenerous in the Opinion of others. I have heard of ſome of their little Arguments (or rather Evaſions) whereby they wou'd fain perſuade them that are Strangers to theſe Affairs, That 'twill be very incommodious, if not impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, to make any Alteration in the preſent Company. As;</p>
               <p>That 'twill be a Work of Time to adjuſt all matters 'twixt the old and new Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers, and ſo may occaſion an Interruption in the Trade, which will be a great Prejudice to the Nation.</p>
               <p>That they have not for ſome Years paſt receiv'd Accounts from their Factors, and are thereby unacquainted with the true State of their Affairs, and Value of their Effects in <hi>India.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That 'twill be a very difficult thing how to compute an equitable Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their dead Stock abroad in <hi>Caſtles, Forts, Colonies, Cities, Towns, Factories,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now beſides the Invalidity of theſe empty Pretences, I cannot but take notice, That our <hi>Cunning Men</hi> are ſometimes ſo unlucky, to outwit themſelves by their own Sophiſms; for certainly 'tis not well conſider'd to give a Hint of the Damage 'twould be to the Publick, to have the Trade interrupted for a little time, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may give occaſion to the Government, to make ſtricter Inquiry into the Reaſon of the late Interruption for four or five Years together, and to exact ſatisfaction for the great Loſs ſuſtain'd thereby, which, as I before intimated, cannot be compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at leſs than a Million to the Crown and the Company.</p>
               <p>Nor will it paſs for better than a Blunder in the School of Politicks, To bring upon the Stage an Accuſation againſt their Servants, in alledging they are ſo long behind in their Accounts; Becauſe ſuch unpardonable Failures abroad, will arraign the Underſtanding or Integrity of <hi>Some body</hi> at home, who has had the choice of all their Servants for ſeveral Years paſt; and make it manifeſt, that there has been Care taken to provide Perſons, juſt ſo fit to aſſiſt in their Mercantile Affairs, <hi>as Coachmen wou'd be to command their Ships.</hi> But moreover this Thing is not more <hi>improper</hi> to be offer'd, than 'tis in part, if not altogether <hi>falſe;</hi> for to my certain knowledg there were General Books of Accounts brought from <hi>Fort St. George</hi> by the <hi>Chandois,</hi> in the beginning of <hi>February</hi> laſt, tho I cannot ſay they are now where they ought to be, in the Companies Houſe in <hi>Leaden-Hall-ſtreet,</hi> for I have been told that a certain Man, who is at preſent no more than one of the Committee, did lately take away ſeveral of their Books and Papers to his own Houſe about ſix Miles from <hi>London;</hi> which, if true, is in my Opinion a ſort of <hi>Felony</hi> that ought not to have the <hi>Benefit of Clergy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to their dead Stock, what I have already ſaid concerning it, will vouch for me, That 'tis as far from my <hi>Will,</hi> as my <hi>Power,</hi> to deny them full Satisfaction for every particular. But I muſt here ſay, 'Tis very idle (I had a'moſt ſaid ridiculous) in thoſe that pretend 'twill be ſuch an inſuperable Difficulty to make a reaſonable Valuation of it. For 'tis but doing over again, what has been done ſeveral times before,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107843:7"/>and the very ſame thing that this Company did to the preceeding. Wherefore however they expreſs themſelves about this Concern, their Meaning is plain, and the Uſe they hope to make of it is this; That if it do's them no further Service, 'twill help to prepoſſeſs People with an Opinion, that it muſt needs be for ſome <hi>mighty Things</hi> that they make ſo great a <hi>Noiſe,</hi> and ſo it may prepare the way to make <hi>a Noble of Nine-pence</hi> by a more current over-valuing thoſe matters, when they come to an Adjuſtment of them. Thus do our ſage Seniors, who have made their <hi>Will</hi> a <hi>Law</hi> to the other Adventurers, and us'd the Committee as the <hi>French</hi> King do's his Parliament at <hi>Paris,</hi> contrive to impoſe on the whole <hi>Nation</hi> at once. But their Wits that have ſerv'd them ſo well in other Attempts, will fail them in this. For as I hope there is no Man wiſhes them the leaſt wrong, ſo I know there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral now in <hi>England,</hi> who can, and I'm ſure will, do a general Right by an Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Account and Eſtimate of all thoſe Particulars.</p>
               <p>They are pleas'd to make uſe of a great many ſeveral <hi>Names,</hi> but all the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sounds ſignifie <hi>one Thing,</hi> when we ſpeak of what may be accounted really conſiderable, and that is their Fortifications of <hi>Bombay</hi> and <hi>Fort St. George.</hi> And becauſe there are ſome, who have given themſelves <hi>a looſe</hi> to ſay any thing, and publiſh'd what they dar'd not own, to magnifie our Companies Intereſt at thoſe Places far above its juſt worth, I cannot forbear to aſſert, what I'm ſure the true Reaſon of the Thing will juſtifie, <hi>That he who thinks thoſe, or any other Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications in the</hi> Mogul's <hi>Dominions, can be of good uſe to us, longer than we hold a Friendſhip with the Government of the Country, had better keep his Opinion to himſelf, than expoſe his Ignorance in the Affairs of</hi> India. And I cannot fear that thoſe who judg according to the true merits of the Cauſe, will ſuſpect me the leſs devoted to the Service of my Country, or the Welfare of the Company, when I declare, That were it not more for the <hi>Diſhonour,</hi> than any other real <hi>Diſ-Intereſt</hi> to the Nation, I cou'd heartily wiſh, Both thoſe <hi>Forts</hi> now in the <hi>Mogul</hi>'s Poſſeſſion. For 'tis a certain Truth, That to have a prudent and intelligent Perſon always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident at the Court of that Great Prince, would ſignifie more to our Security and Advantage, than Ten Fortifications, and coſt leſs than the tenth Part of the Charge of One. I ſay this with the more Aſſurance, from the great Things I have ſeen done by ſome ingenious Gentlemen, Chiefs of the Companies Factories, who were duly ſenſible of what great Import it was, to have a good Friend, or a faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant continually attending at Court, and acted accordingly. For I was in <hi>Bengale</hi> when Mr. <hi>Shem Bridges</hi> did ſuperintend their Affairs in thoſe Parts, and he had on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Houſe for the Reſidence of the Factory, wherein I am ſure he cou'd no more pretend to any Strength ſufficient to offend, or defend himſelf from the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Country, than a ſingle Gentleman amongſt us can engage with a whole County; Yet I ſaw, That by the good Correſpondence he kept at the Court of the <hi>Mogul</hi>'s Vice Roy in that Kingdom, and by his great Prudence in his Converſe and Intercourſes with the People, he did not only live ſecure, with the Companies Affairs flouriſhing under his judicious Direction; but he obtain'd to exerciſe a <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction</hi> there: and for any Affronts, Frauds, or Failures, he did impriſon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, And inflicted what corporal Puniſhment he pleas'd not extending to Life. And ſuch was his Art and Management in all Reſpects, as did great Honour to the Nation, and made himſelf belov'd or fear'd by all about him.</p>
               <p>The like Encomiums are alſo juſtly due to Mr. <hi>William Jearſey</hi> formerly Chief at <hi>Metchlepatan,</hi> where he had nothing more like a Fortreſs, than a Houſe in the midſt of a populous Town, contiguous with other Buildings: But he found out Ways of making ſo potent an Intereſt at the Court of <hi>Golcondah,</hi> as not only gave him a general great Reſpect, and remov'd all Obſtructions in his Buſineſs with the Merchants and People of the Country; But the very Governors ſtood in ſome awe of him: And one great Thing he did for our Honour and Intereſt, ought not to be forgot, tho I fear 'twill never be requited, which was his ſaving the Ship <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> Merchant, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken, in the firſt War the late King <hi>Charles</hi> made with the <hi>Dutch.</hi> That Ship was riding in the open Road of <hi>Metchlepatan,</hi> when our Enemies ſent Three or Four Ships of War to ſeize her, but this Gentleman had made timely and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Proviſion to fruſtrate their Deſign. For he obtain'd a poſitive Command from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107843:8"/>the King to the Governour of the Province, to bring a Force before the <hi>Dutch Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,</hi> and threaten Deſtruction to them and all they had there, in caſe they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd any Violence to our Ship in the Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> cool'd their Courage, that they let her remain peaceably to take in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wherewith ſhe afterwards ſafely arriv'd in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I hope I ſhall not be miſunderſtood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Things, and while I am purſuing Truth, be ſuſpected to have any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Preſent Companies Prejudice; Or that I would have it inferr'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> I have ſaid, That <hi>Fort S. George</hi> and <hi>Bombay</hi> are of no value. I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> my Intentions, and I muſt declare my ſelf of a contrary O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                     <desc>••••…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> have them, I think we are under a Neceſſity of endeavouring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Juſtice will require, That this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany have a reaſonable Conſidera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r what they preſented to the Crown for the one, and paid to their Predeceſſors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the other, together with what more may have been ſince expended in neceſſary and uſeful Additions to them.</p>
               <p>And truly I am ſorry for their ſakes, I cannot ſay the ſame thing for their new Garriſon at <hi>Tegnapatan,</hi> whereof we had lately an Account in the Gazet, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting us, That they had purchas'd it for about Twelve Thouſand Pounds. I know the Place, and ſhould have been glad in their behalf, if in the room of that Intelligence they had heard of ſome unavoidable Loſs to the like amount, for then they had known the worſt at once: But I doubt the next Letters will bring them a melancholy Account of the growing Charge in repairing that ruinous Building, and accommodating its many Wants; and when all that is done, there can no more be made of it, than <hi>a New Thing, and nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I leave theſe Things to be more particularly inſpected and examin'd by thoſe may have it in Charge to conſider of them; and what I have now farther to offer, is, That I am well aſſur'd all theſe Remora's wherewith the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to obſtruct a happy Reform and Re-eſtabliſhment of this Trade, will be effectually remov'd; If the Parliament ſhall in their great Wiſdom ſee Cauſe to give Life to the Great and Good Work, by encouraging a <hi>National Subſcription</hi> to be conjoyn'd to the Nett Remains of the Preſent Stock for a <hi>Grand Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital.</hi> Something of this kind notifi'd to the Publick, and the negotiating Part recommended to a Committee of Merchants, whoſe Parts and Probity qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie them for this Occaſion, wou'd moſt certainly in the Term of five or ſix Weeks accompliſh the matter in readineſs to be reported for further Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration concerning the eſtabliſhing this <hi>National Company</hi> by a Law. And for the ſpeedier perfecting the whole Matter, The very ſame Gentlemen that ſhall be Commiſſioned for the new Subſcriptions, may be conjoyn'd with the like Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Members of the Committee for the preſent Company, and at the ſame time proceed in adjuſting the value of things that are to be incorporated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>National Stock,</hi> having Power to examine Perſons upon Oath, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect all Books, Papers and Records as they ſhall find requiſite for their Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thus, with the Aſſiſtance of the preſent Accomptant General Mr. <hi>Buyer,</hi> who has ſo great Knowledge in the liberal Science he profeſſes, That all <hi>Europe</hi> cannot produce one who excells, and but a very few that equal him; together with the Notices may be receiv'd of ſeveral Gentlemen who have reſided in <hi>India,</hi> and are well acquainted with the Nature and Condition of every thing relating to the Company there; <hi>The great Affair</hi> cannot fail to be fully effected in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Term, and in the Interim Ships will be fitting, and may well be in readineſs for diſpatch to the ſeveral Parts of <hi>India,</hi> 'twixt the beginning of <hi>January</hi> and the end of <hi>March</hi> next, which is the moſt proper Seaſon. So that the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> may be at eaſe, and no longer diſturb themſelves with anxious Doubts and Fears of any Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption happening to the Trade, by this moſt deſirable Revolution and Fixation of it.</p>
               <p>The next great Conſideration is, concerning a Committee to manage this <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Stock.</hi> And where there muſt be ſo great a Truſt repos'd, there cannot be too much Care taken in the choice. For 'tis not only, That that wicked Thing of <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing the Man by his Stock,</hi> muſt be anathematiz'd, and never ſo much as nam'd amongſt us, but all poſſible Cautions muſt be us'd, That the Elections be intirely
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107843:8"/>influenc'd and guided by thoſe intrinſick Recommendations of <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> abſtracted from all other Invitations or Motives whatſoever.</p>
               <p>But after all that Care which Human Providence is capable of, in laying the Foundation of this noble Enterprize; There is one important thing more muſt be done with the firſt beginning of the Superſtructure, if ever we hope to erect a Glorious Fabrick; And that is, The obtaining of Their Majeſties the Grace and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to ſend an Ambaſſador in their Royal Name, to the Great <hi>Mogul, to retrieve our loſt Eſteem, and reinſtate us in our Commerce on Honourable and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Terms,</hi> which I am very ſure may be effectually done by proper Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from a Perſon of good Port and Conduct: And 'twill much facilitate his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, by giving an acceptable Proof of our Intentions to become the ſame <hi>honeſt Engliſh Men</hi> they have formerly known us, If that Part of what the preſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany have taken from the People of <hi>Suratt,</hi> and is now here in their Poſſeſſion, be return'd by his Lordſhips hands to be reſtor'd to the Right-Owners. Nor ſhall we herein only advance our Reputation to the higheſt Degree with that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but ſuch a <hi>meritorious Action</hi> at our Entrance, will be a moſt effectual means <hi>to attack Heaven itſelf by a holy Violence, and ſecure the Divine Benediction to our future Adventures.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="continuation_of_letter">
               <p>I Have thus, Right Honourable and Moſt Honoured SIRS, endeavour'd to diſcharge the Duty incumbent on me by your Command, and I have done it faithfully; for whatever I have aſſerted as matter of Fact, I am ready to Prove by full and particular Evidence: And wherein I have offer'd my Opinion, I have impartially ſet down thoſe Sentiments which my Acquaintance with theſe Affairs dictated to me. And now, if I may hope what I have ſaid ſufficient to convince, That the Trade to <hi>India</hi> is worthy your Regard, and That the Honour and Intereſt of the Nation do's indiſpenſibly require ſome ſpeedy and effectual Care for the Preſervation of it; Then I am well aſſur'd, The ſame good Principle that prompted you to demand this Paper of me, will alſo incite you to make uſe of all your Intereſt and Influence with the Government, in promoting the happy Eſtabliſhment thereof; Whereby you will do a moſt beneficial and acceptable Service to the whole Kingdom, and in a moſt eſpecial manner highly oblige thoſe honeſt <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>Merchants</hi> who have a right Cogniſance and Eſteem of this grand Concern: Amongſt whom, I beg leave in the loweſt Poſture of Reſpect to render the moſt humble and moſt grateful Acknowledgment, of</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>Moſt Noble</hi> LORDS, <hi>and moſt Honoured</hi> SIRS, </salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt Obedient And moſt faithful Servant, <hi>GEORGE WHITE.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
